Guide to the Anna Biedel Weitz Papers 1904-1983
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Anna Biedel Weitz Papers
1904-1983
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 158
Weitz, Anna Biedel
0.5 Linear feet of shelf space 1 Box
This collection records the history of the town of Endicott, Washington through correspondence, clippings, prose, a scrapbook, and other materials written, collected, or compiled by Anna Biedel Weitz.
Anna Biedel Weitz (1907-1985) was married to Alex L. Weitz and lived in Endicott, Washington where she took on numerous roles in the small town. Primarily, Weitz worked with her husband at his insurance agency where she wrote wills as a German-English interpreter, obtained delayed birth certificates, and performed other miscellaneous duties for her husband's company. Weitz also published the town's weekly newspaper, the Endicott Index, for eight years, and compiled a town history.
This collection contains correspondence, clippings, a scrapbook, and other materials relating to the history of Endicott, Washington, all written, collected, or compiled by Anna Biedel Weitz of Endicott. The materials date from 1904 to 1983. Weitz's research encompassed the town's schools, churches, lodges, clubs, railroads, telephone system, etc. A scrapbook of newspaper clippings is included in the collection, chronicling the history of Endicott. This series, titled "The Blue Mirror," appeared in the Endicott Index in 1935 and was written by Miss E. Deane Smith. There is also a history of the town written by Earl Miller.
In addition to Weitz's historical information on the town, the collection includes her own writings, several published in 1986: "The Volga-German epicure," "Country Lanes," "Victory Parade," "With Freedom's Holy Light," and many others.
This collection is arranged in a single series.
This collection is open and available for research use.
This collection was donated to the Washington State University Libraries in 1963-1971 by Anna Biedel Weitz. Additional materials were received and added to the collection in 1980.
Brumley, Howard J., 1905-. The Weitz Saga. [Place of publication not identified] :H.J. Brumley, 1986.
Weitz, Anna Biedel. The Volga-German Epicure. East Detroit, Mich. (22444 Kelly Rd., Apt. 2, East Detroit 480921): Howard J. Brumley, 1986.
Weitz, Anna Biedel. Country Lanes. East Detroit, Mich.: H.J. Brumley, Sr., 1986.
Scheuerman/Lust Family Confirmation Certificates, 1899-1924 (MS 2020.23)
Richard D. Scheuerman Volga German Papers, 1766-2009 (MS 2021.17)
Emma Schwabenland Haynes Papers, 1927-1982 (Cage 573)
American Historical Society of Germans from Russia Records, 1968-1984 (Cage 850)
Fred C. Koch Papers, 1802-1983 (Cage 851)
Emma Schwabenland Haynes Nuremberg Papers, 1940-1984 (Cage 953)
Dewald Family Story Typescript, 1998 (Cage 4827)
Arthur Hartwig Notes on Germans from Russia, 1916-1999 (Cage 5085)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Weitz, Anna Biedel -- Archives
Endicott (Wash.) -- History -- Sources
Russian Germans -- Washington (State) -- History
German Americans; Russian Americans; Washington (State)
- Prose and poetry: "The Volga-German epicure," "Granny is too Old," "They Waged and Won," "Tales of My People," "A Wonderful and Waning Language", 1941-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Endicott, Washington history, 1904, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Endicott, Washington school history: graduation announcements, clippings, correspondence, etc., 1904-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Telephone directories, 1961-1962 and undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Xerox notes and papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "With Freedom's Holy Light" by Anna Biedel Weitz, circa 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Church - history and anniversary announcements, circa 1934-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Country Lanes" and "Victory Parade" by Anna Biedel Weitz, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Lodges, clubs, railroads, and shipping history, 1904-1917, 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Scrapbook of Endicott, Washington history: "The Blue Mirror" by Miss E. Deane Smith, 1911-1918, 1935-1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)